<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Life and death of Ralph Wallis, the cobbler of Glocester together with some inquiring into the mystery of conventicleism.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 95KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 24 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A48400</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12609138</idno>
  <idno type="VID">64305</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2248569628</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing L2008</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R20134</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">12609138</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A48400)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 64305)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 964:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Life and death of Ralph Wallis, the cobbler of Glocester together with some inquiring into the mystery of conventicleism.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[3], 43 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by E. Okes for William Whitwood,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1670.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="personal_name">Wallis, Ralph, d. 1669.</term>
               <term type="geographic_name">Great Britain --  History --  1660-1714.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-05 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-11 </date>
            <label>Kate Allen </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-11 </date>
            <label>Kate Allen</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:64305:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:64305:1"/>
            <p>THE Life and Death OF <hi>RALPH WALLIS</hi> The <hi>COBLER</hi> of GLOCESTER: Together with some inquiring into the Mystery of Conventicleism.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Miscemus multis seria multa jocis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>E. Okes,</hi> for <hi>William Whit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood.</hi> 1670.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:64305:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:64305:2"/>
            <head>The Preface.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Ampridius</hi> writing the lives of several Roman Emperours, when he came down to <hi>Heliogaba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus,</hi> made a stand, Debating with himself whether or no he ought to write his life also, which because it was so bad, he thought 'twas best to pass by in silence; but then considering that the lives of <hi>Caligula, Nero, Vitellus,</hi> and other wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Emperours stood registred to posterity, he thereupon put the life of that Monster of Mankind <hi>Heliogabalus,</hi> upon the file of time, also the like conflict had I with my self essaying to write the life of the wicked <hi>Cobler</hi> of <hi>Glocester,</hi> but finding that the lives of <hi>German Lazarillous Hanham,</hi> and other Thieves and Rogues were upon Record, I thereupon resolved to picture this <hi>Cobler</hi> as near the life as I could, which I tell you before hand will be a very deformed piece; had I a mind to bely him, I could hardly do it, he was so bad of himself, and he said and did so ill against the living while he was amongst them, that it is no wonder if you find not one good word of him here, now he is dead. My design in writing his life, is to acquaint the world who it was that so troubled it with scrawling and bawling against the Church, and it's Ministers, that thereby the rigorous censures of all, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>justly conceived against it and them by the injurious tongue and pen of the <hi>Cobler</hi> may be mitigated. And truly the World had had this account of him long ago, had not I expected that some <hi>Tyburnian Chronologer,</hi> or Ballad-maker (for whom this Subject is most proper) would e're this have put out some Relation of him, and got it cry'd in the streets with the lives of the two <hi>Dudley's</hi> and <hi>Damaris Page:</hi> but finding that those <hi>Red Lattice Historians</hi> are silent, I have taken this pains but just time enough to prevent <hi>Poor Robins Almanack</hi> to tell you who and what this Cobler was.</p>
            <p>He was a base Instrument, which the Fanaticks us'd to rake
<pb facs="tcp:64305:3"/> in dirt with, that they might not foul their own fingers. He was their Champion to encounter the Church, and pull the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shops thence, a the <hi>Gyants</hi> of old did Heaven to dethron the Gods, and to this end he was f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rnish'd by them (instead of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Amunition) with Pamphlets and Libels, and charg'd up to the mouth with lyes and slanders, which he let flye (like hail-shot) against the Church and Church-men, to bespatter it's Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, and their Lives.</p>
            <p>The Fanaticks Triumph'd in him over the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> because (although he gave them so many just provoca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ions, by writing and speaking dishonourably of them) none ever an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer'd him. But let not the Fanaticks imagine it was so hard a matter to confute the Cobler as <hi>Bellermin.</hi> I would have them know, it was the innocency and moderation of the scandalized Church-men that advised them not to descend to take notice of what the Conventicle-leaders said and writ by the mouth and pen of this wicked Cobler against them. It is far below the generosi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of any Christian Church-men to be mov'd at the calumnies and ignominious imputations of the <hi>Mountebank</hi> Ministers, or their degenerate <hi>Merry Andrew-like Cobler,</hi> for they prudent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly agree with <hi>Tacitus,</hi> that <hi>Maledicta spreta exolescunt,</hi> and like that <hi>magnanimus injuriarum contemptor Socrates,</hi> dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain to be angry at the kicking of Asses and barking of Dogs (for such were the Cobler and those his instigators, continually kicking a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the Government, and barking against Caelestial bodies.) They hold it to be <hi>praestantissimum ultionis genus rebus ipsis et mori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus confutare hanc Zoylorum sectam, quae in eorum acta tam sedulo inquirant ut ea fingant quae nunquam fuere;</hi> and can say of such their malevolent calumniators (as <hi>Philip Alexanders</hi> Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther said of the <hi>Athenians) quod assiduis eorum convitiis meli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ores in dies efficiantur et diligentius vitam instituant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now let any wise man judge by this following relation, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the <hi>Cobler</hi> did not deserve contempt, the <hi>Conventicle-lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders</hi> his stimulators punishment, and their <hi>followers</hi> pitty.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="biography">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:64305:3"/>
            <head>The LIFE and DEATH OF <hi>RALPH WALLIS</hi> THE COBLER of <hi>GLOCESTER.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Am not so good a Herauld as to tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>slate <hi>this Translator</hi> out of his Original: wherefore to begin with him, letting his nasty Pedegree alone, I look upon him as a <hi>Mushrom</hi> sprung up in the late Dung-hill Times, which gave growth to many such base Weeds, and kept under more generous Plants: An <hi>Upstart</hi> was then no Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digy, there were many then extracted something out of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing by a strange Chymical Art much in practise in those daies: It was ordinary to see a <hi>Gentleman</hi> or a <hi>Preacher</hi> ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerated out of the corruption of a <hi>Souldier</hi> or a <hi>Tradesman;</hi> amongst the rest the obscure <hi>Cobler</hi> began to conceive high thoughts, being bob'd o'th' Elbow by the daily examples of many <hi>Heroique Upstarts,</hi> who advanc'd themselves from as mean Originals as his own: The Trophies of <hi>Miltiades</hi>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:64305:4"/> would not let <hi>Themistocles</hi> take his rest, neither could the <hi>Cobler</hi> be quiet for Emulation; he saw that <hi>Vavasor Powel</hi> had thrown away his Curry Comb, disdaining any longer to be an Hostler; <hi>Zachary Crofton</hi> had left his Counter, and that the celebrated Saint of <hi>Salisbury-Court, Farington,</hi> had lept from his Loom; and therefore the <hi>Cobler</hi> saw no reason why he might not as well bounce from his Bulk; nay, which is more, this single-sol'd <hi>Cobler</hi> saw his single-ey'd Brother <hi>Huson</hi> making himself great by his Sword, and why might not he open a Trap-door to his Fortune by some Pick-lock way or other; one <hi>Cobler</hi> had as much impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, and as little honesty, as the other: <hi>Ralph Wallis</hi> had a face of as good mettle, as <hi>Husons</hi> Armor, and time dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover'd that he was as stout a Brother of the Quill, as <hi>Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son</hi> was of the Blade; nay, he had this signal advantage o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver him, for whereas <hi>Huson</hi> having but one eye might be taken o'th' blind side, <hi>Ralph Wallis</hi> could brag with the men of <hi>China,</hi> that he saw with two eyes.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Cobler of Glocester</hi>'s ambition being thus set on edge by the daily preferment of his Brother Rogues, he calls a Councel of his own, and his Wife's wit, to know how his watering chops also might tast the sweetness of those licen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious times; after mature chew of the Cud, it was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded, that <hi>Religion,</hi> that profitable Craft, should be the first way for him to raise his Fortune by; whereupon to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin the work of Reformation upon himself, he left off tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning <hi>Ballads,</hi> and fell a singing <hi>Psalms,</hi> both in's House and Stall; and though 'twas a hard matter for him, being a <hi>Cobler,</hi> to leave off <hi>Whistling,</hi> yet he made sure never to whistle, but to the tune of some of <hi>Robert Wisdome, Thomas Sternhold,</hi> or <hi>John Hopkins</hi> Meeter. So a certain Colonel, to give God thanks for the Kings defeat at <hi>Worcester,</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stead of singing a <hi>Te Deum,</hi> said to his Troop, <hi>Let us whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stle to the praise of God the hundredth Psalm.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:64305:4"/>
            <p>The <hi>Cobler</hi> would whistle and sing Psalms from four in the morning till twelve at night, to the great disturbance of many weary Travellers that lay near him: but by this means he got himself the reputation of a <hi>Religious Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour</hi> amongst the Godly of <hi>Glocester,</hi> who for his pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Piety let him have the mending of all their old Shoes, and gave him many a Sundays Dinner, and afternoons Lun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chin.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Cobler</hi> animated with this good success of his sing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, made no question but that in time he might arrive to the faculty of <hi>Canting,</hi> and by that means exchange his <hi>Cobling Trade</hi> for a <hi>Saintship,</hi> yet he was a little discoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged for the present, being that like a true <hi>Cobler,</hi> he could neither write nor read: but that obstacle was quickly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mov'd, for his <hi>Wife,</hi> who no doubt had a Prophetical Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, having it one night reveal'd by her Familiar in a dream, that one time or other her Husband would deserve hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, advis'd him by all means to put himself into a capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city of claiming the benefit of the Clergy; whereupon ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king his Wife's admonition, he fell to his Horn-book, and being a little acquainted with his Letters, he skipt over to the Testament, not taking the Primer and Psalter in's way, because they had <hi>Common Prayer</hi> in their Bellies; and thus with much pains, and his Wife's great care, he learnt his Neck-verse; and considering that the Art of Writing might stand him in as good stead, he by some means or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther learnt to scraul a little false English.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Cobler</hi> was scarce able to read the Scripture, but he took upon him the <hi>Interpretation</hi> of it; for finding it writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, that <hi>Paul</hi> wrought with his own hands, he thought he might probably be a <hi>Cobler;</hi> nay, this <hi>Cordwainer</hi> would undertake to enter into the most intricate <hi>Labyrinth</hi> of Scripture, and come out again the right way, by the Cord or Clew of his own imagination.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:64305:5"/>
            <p>By this time his Shop was too little to hold him, he would not hide his Farthing Candle under a Bushel, nor bury his <hi>two pcny Talent</hi> in the ground, but he pack'd up his Awls, and out he went; to proclaim how much the Riches of Grace were advanc'd in an empty <hi>nothing Cobler.</hi> Long he had not been out of his Bulk, e're he was receiv'd into several silly Widdows houses, who for the seeming Sanctity of his Conversation, suffer'd him to exercise his Gifts amongst them; and when any Master of a Family went from home, he commonly supply'd his absence, do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all kinds of Family Duty at his house; for which his service, he usually got his paunch fill'd, and something else.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Cobler</hi> having thus renounced the Order of <hi>Saint Hugh,</hi> might have liv'd very plentifully upon the Incomes of his Prayers, which like <hi>Peters</hi> Fish, afforded him both meat and money; but yet finding his Fortune too low roof'd for his high spirit, and this praying Profession too strict for his boundless mind, he soon became weary of it, and turn'd it off like an unprofitable servant; and being of a Nature more inclin'd to trouble then quietness, he fell a repining at his low condition, and thought to raise it by impoverishing others: This made him so ready to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take that Hangman-like imployment under <hi>Olivers Commis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sioners,</hi> of being an <hi>Under-Sequestrator</hi> of the Loyal Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties Goods, in which Office he was as cruel as a common Executioner, insulting over the Loyalists adversity: Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sides, he was <hi>a Knight of the Post</hi> to the <hi>Oliverian</hi> Crew, for when ever they suspected any Gentleman guilty of the Crime of being true to his King and Conscience, or were jealous that any honest Minister stood disaffected to <hi>Olivers</hi> Government over the Church or State, <hi>Ralph Wallis,</hi> the <hi>Cobler of Glocester,</hi> would offer himself for a small sum to be an <hi>Informer,</hi> or <hi>Journey-man-Swearer</hi> against them:
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:64305:5"/> But this imployment also he left off, not out of any honest Principle, but because he was usually cheated of the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges he was promis'd for his Perjury, at which he took such distast, that he fell a railing against them that set him on that wicked work: But besides this his just displeasure conceived against the Government, he had a strange Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pathy to any <hi>Power,</hi> and like a true <hi>Sectary,</hi> he could not be quiet under any <hi>Government</hi> long. And hence it was that he rail'd so against <hi>Oliver</hi> and the <hi>Rump-Parliament,</hi> fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering several nameless Pamphlets put out against them.</p>
            <p>Had he cry'd down <hi>Olivers</hi> Power, that this might have come up, there had been something to have commended him for; but 'tis certain he had no other design but to shew his general Enmity to any Power, in venturing his Neck so in <hi>Olivers</hi> time, that doubtless he had been hang'd, and so fulfill'd his Wife's Dream, had not the Devil, <hi>his back-friend,</hi> preserv'd him to do him more such service in this Government, as I shall relate.</p>
            <p>When the <hi>Ramp</hi> was unroosted, which all the time it sate hatch'd many ungodly Chucks, amongst other good Reformations, the Churches, which had a long time been <hi>Dens of Thieves,</hi> became <hi>Houses of Prayer</hi> again, and the <hi>Upstart-Gospellers</hi> were dispossessed of their usurped Benefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, who fearing least their Kingdome should be now at an end, and that they should return to their <hi>Shops</hi> again, which they had so advantagiously exchang'd for <hi>Pulpits,</hi> (like as the Legion of Devils chose rather to enter into an Herd of Swine, then to return to the place from whence they came) entred into an Herd of dull, melancholly, ill-look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and worse-meaning people, chusing rather to get their livings by leading them like <hi>Owls</hi> into Barns and by- places, and teaching them to repine against the Government, then honestly to thrive in the Callings wherein their mean For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes at first plac'd them.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:64305:6"/>
            <p>These <hi>Handy-craft-Preachers,</hi> like the Masters of the <hi>South-saying-Damsel,</hi> seeing the hope of their gains was like to be gone, did like <hi>Demetrius</hi> the <hi>Silver-Smith,</hi> call together their Fellow <hi>Crafts-men,</hi> who considering in what peril their advantagious Craft was to come to nought, put all the Towns and Cities into such uproars, that the <hi>Town-Clerks</hi> and Magistrates cannot quiet them.</p>
            <p>These <hi>Mecanick Ministers,</hi> and other <hi>Changling Church-men,</hi> being vext they made no more hast to be rich while their Sun shin'd, by all sinister means endeavour to bring all things into the same confusion again; to which intent they have got on their side all those that entred into that Solemn League and Covenant of living and dying <hi>Rebels,</hi> and all that tasted the sweetness of the late <hi>licentious</hi> times, who like Kill-sheep dogs, impatient of restraint, would fain be ravening aga<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n, and therefore Cur-like they snarl at the Magistrates of Church and State, howling and cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out for Liberty of Conscience, saying, 'twill never be well till there be an <hi>Amsterdam</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> that every man may do what is right in his own eyes, by all which they mean an <hi>Ambuscado,</hi> for their further impious de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>signs.</p>
            <p>These kind of malevolent people, I say, from the first de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sign'd the ruine of the present Government; but consider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it must be a work of time and policy, like great <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiavillians,</hi> they made choice of that seldome-failing Stratagem, <hi>Zeal for Reformation in Religion,</hi> to encrease their own Party by, and lessen the power of them in Rule; whereupon the <hi>Pulpiteers</hi> of this disaffected Faction entring into private Assemblies, fell a Praying and Preaching (as they do still) against the times, deriding the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Church, and crying out for Reformation thereof; thus warring against the <hi>Bishops,</hi> that they may a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain triumph over the King.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:64305:6"/>
            <p>Herein they were great <hi>Polititians</hi> indeed, and cunning<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly consider'd, that the most impious designs were usually palliated with the most specious pretexts of Piety, they well remembred how successful the <hi>Pulpit</hi> had been in for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Rebellions, and that no wicked Plot was ever laid without some <hi>Preacher</hi> in it; they call'd to mind, how that the Famous General <hi>Jack Straw</hi>'s endeavours had been in vain, without the strong assistance of <hi>Parson Ball;</hi> how the <hi>Gunpowder Plot</hi> had never been laid, without the contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance of <hi>Father Garnet;</hi> and how <hi>Oliver Cromwel</hi> had never been <hi>Lord Protector,</hi> had not his <hi>Black Coats</hi> laid about them in the <hi>Pulpits,</hi> as his <hi>Red Coats</hi> did in the <hi>Field.</hi> King <hi>John</hi> was poysoned by a <hi>Monk,</hi> King <hi>Henry</hi> of <hi>France</hi> was stabb'd by a <hi>Jacobin Fryer,</hi> and our late <hi>Soveraign</hi> was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn'd from the <hi>Pulpit,</hi> e're he had his Sentence from the <hi>Bench;</hi> and so was his Loyal Subject <hi>Montrose</hi> in <hi>Scotland.</hi> The <hi>Pope</hi> can do more with his Swarms of <hi>Fryers and Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suites,</hi> then with Regiments of Horse and Foot. All this (I say) was well known to the disaffected Faction, who to bring about their designs, thought it good policy to have a <hi>Regiment of private Gospellers</hi> also scatter'd up and down, which like Fiered Beacons might alarum their whole For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces to rise when they saw opportunity.</p>
            <p>Besides these <hi>Privateers,</hi> they had certain <hi>Emissaries</hi> or Factors of their Faction in several parts, which like Incen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diary <hi>Jesuites</hi> might enter into Churches and Houses to raise <hi>Mutinies</hi> amongst the people against their <hi>Ministers;</hi> and by prying into their discontents, by deceiving them with Lies and Scandals upon <hi>Episcopacy,</hi> and by using any kind of wicked means whatsoever, might make them <hi>Rebels</hi> to the <hi>Church,</hi> and <hi>Turn-coats</hi> to <hi>Conventicles.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Amongst other <hi>Whelps</hi> of this Litter, the <hi>Cobler of Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cester</hi> having got himself the reputation of an <hi>Ingenious man,</hi> in reference to any kind of mischief, that the Devil, Man, or
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:64305:7"/> his own wicked invention could prompt him to, was look'd upon as a <hi>Person</hi> very fitly qualifi'd for this Imployment; and he finding it like to prove a thriving way, needed no stronger invitation then his own <hi>poverty</hi> to tempt him to't, for so he could but make his <hi>cloaths</hi> whole, he car'd not though 'twas by making Rents and Divisions in the Church. He therefore readily fell to his task, which was to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert, divert, and pervert all the seduceable people he could meet with, sending them like Sheep to his Neighbouring <hi>Conventicle Leaders,</hi> who were to give him a share of their <hi>Golden Fleeces.</hi> He was also to invent Lyes, and raise Calumnies upon the Church and Church-men: He was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so to Father <hi>Libels,</hi> and scatter <hi>Pamphlets,</hi> tending to the dishonor of the Church; and in a word, to do any base thing that <hi>Conventicle Leaders,</hi> and others his Abettors and Pay-masters should put him upon: He had assign'd him for a Province to exercise his Rogueries in, all <hi>Glocester<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shire,</hi> but all <hi>England</hi> was a limit narrow enough for him to expatiate his mighty self in, for his Legs and Tongue were in continual motion, and both body and mind were always rambling; and in all parts where ever he came, he was so nimble an <hi>Agent</hi> for <hi>Non-conformity,</hi> that <hi>West<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minster Hall</hi> is not so much beholding to all the <hi>Green Bags</hi> in <hi>England</hi> together, for creating Law-suits, as the <hi>Fanatick Faction</hi> was to this their great <hi>Minister,</hi> the <hi>Cobler of Gloce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster,</hi> for the multitude of <hi>Non-conformists.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>No man cry'd louder for a <hi>Toleration, and Liberty of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science;</hi> no man cast more dirt upon the <hi>Lawn</hi> and <hi>Holland</hi> of the Church; no man more furious against the Eaters of <hi>Plum-broth,</hi> and Minc'd Pyes at <hi>Christmass,</hi> though he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self would as greedily devour those <hi>Superstitious meats</hi> then, as Flesh in <hi>Lent</hi> and <hi>Ember weeks;</hi> no man a greater E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy to any kind of decency; no man a greater Abuser of the <hi>Clergy,</hi> witness his <hi>Dialogue</hi> betwixt him and his <hi>Wife,</hi>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:64305:7"/> where he lays faults to their charge that never were com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, just like a <hi>Tyburn Poet,</hi> that commonly gets a lying Relation of the Malefactors Execution printed e're they suffer; nay, he would not only belye the Church, but the Court also; for having somewhere heard that <hi>Drollery</hi> was much in fashion there, he gave out in the Country, that the Court was full of <hi>Idolatry:</hi> He would call the <hi>Common Prayer</hi> as bad as a <hi>Common Whore,</hi> and say it had swearing and cursing in it: He would mock the <hi>Organs,</hi> and singing men, in a tone as ugly as the <hi>howling of a Dog,</hi> and call a <hi>Surplis,</hi> Scarfe and Scarlet, the very Smock, Hood, and Petticoat of the Whore of <hi>Babylon;</hi> he would rail without either fear or wit against the Magistrates and Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisters, contemning their power, and slandering their lives; he had an inveterate malice against <hi>Ecclesiastical Jurisdicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> because he was too wicked to live under it, and he hated a <hi>Chancellor</hi> as an untoward Boy doth his School-master: He would speak <hi>Treason</hi> as familiarly as Non-sense, and sometimes he would <hi>blaspheme,</hi> to shew he nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther car'd for Earthly nor Heavenly Power.</p>
            <p>He was once Indicted for denying the Kings <hi>Supremacy</hi> over the Church, and being found Guilty, was fin'd twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty pounds, and committed to Prison, where he was or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd to stay until he found sufficient Security for his good behaviour; but he came off more favourably then an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nester man should have done, being favour'd by a certain Officer, who for fear of offending his Wife, and other Saints and Saintesses, set him at liberty e're he had per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed the Order of Court.</p>
            <p>'Tis long of such that Meeting Houses go up faster then Churches in <hi>London,</hi> and I'm afraid there's too many of them that can find in their hearts to contribute to the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recting or hiring of a Meeting House, but take no
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:64305:8"/> more care to have the Churches up again.</p>
            <p>This is much to the purpose, but not so much to the <hi>Cobler</hi> in hand, who (as I said before) was continually scandalizing the Government both of Church and State; and truly it would require a whole Volum to set down all the abuses, injuries, and incivilities he put upon the Church and Church-men; but it shall suffice me to tell you, that as a <hi>Whore</hi> prostitutes her self neither for love nor lust, but only gain, so what ever the <hi>Cobler</hi> wrote, said, or did, to the dishonor of the Government of Church and State, was neither for Conscience nor Religions sake, but only for a few Contributions and Meals Meat, which he had allow'd him from <hi>Conventiclers, and Conventicle Leaders,</hi> some whereof, when ever they had a mind to shew their irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concileable spleen to the Church, and by consequence to the State, would vent it in some scurrilous <hi>Libel</hi> or other, which for a little money they could get the <hi>Cobler</hi> to Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther upon himself, but for his own part he never had any issue of his brain, except that <hi>illegitimate Dialogue,</hi> which he conceived and brought forth in so mis-shappen a Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod, that it would have plainly appear'd to be the work of a <hi>Cobler</hi> indeed, had not some such Abettors of his Facts, as <hi>Conventicle Leaders,</hi> lick'd it, like a <hi>Bear,</hi> into a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle more tollerable shape. In that <hi>Dialogue,</hi> the <hi>Cobler</hi> of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten makes mention of his <hi>Wife,</hi> which shews what use he made of her in all his Counsels. <hi>Lentulus</hi> the <hi>Proconsul,</hi> made great use of his Wife's counsel in all his business: Pope <hi>Innocent</hi> the XIII. advised much with his <hi>Niece:</hi> The Author of the familiar Epistles imparted all his secrets to his <hi>Concubine;</hi> but the <hi>Cobler</hi> made more use of a Woman then they all, for without his Wife he could do nothing; she was a good <hi>Linguist,</hi> and taught him both to read and scold; she was also of a <hi>good invention,</hi> and help'd him
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:64305:8"/> to make Lyes: In a word, she was to him instead of an <hi>Oracle, Sybil, and Familiar,</hi> and if she was not a <hi>Witch,</hi> yet she was foul enough to be suspected for one.</p>
            <p>Many other Books besides this <hi>Dialogue</hi> did the <hi>Cobler</hi> own, though 'tis certain he could never write true Sense, Tense, Case, nor Figure▪ but for all that he had an itching mind to be scribling, and like as <hi>Diogenes</hi> of <hi>Corinth,</hi> see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Countrymen all busie in resisting King <hi>Philips</hi> Siege, least he alone should be idle amongst so many workers, fell a tumbling his <hi>Tub</hi> up and down: So this indefatigable <hi>Cobler</hi> disdaining to be idle amongst so many <hi>Goos-quill men,</hi> who with their addle brains, and idle pens, were daily fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling the world with sedition, cry'd, <hi>Room for the Cobler of Glocester,</hi> and fell a railing, for want of wit and matter, against the times, deriding the Laws, and slandering the Government.</p>
            <p>Resolv'd he was to get himself a Name, and considering he had not <hi>virtues</hi> to do it by, he therefore thriftily man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nag'd his <hi>Vices</hi> to that end, chusing rather to die odiously with <hi>Jack Cade,</hi> and <hi>Wat Tyler,</hi> then to live obscurely.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pausanias</hi> kill'd <hi>Philip</hi> of <hi>Macedon,</hi> that he might be talk'd of to Posterity; and another infamous <hi>Fame-hunter</hi> burnt <hi>Diana</hi>'s Temple; and so the <hi>Cobler</hi> did the King and the Church as much disgrace as he could, that he might get himself a reputation, though 'twas of a <hi>Rogue;</hi> and this made him so ready to own as his Act and Deed so many scandalous and virulent Pamphlets, which 'tis certain he was never the <hi>facinorous</hi> Author of.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Cobler</hi> indeed had <hi>Sulphur</hi> enough, though not <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cury</hi> in him to compass such abusive stuff, and how drossy soever his writings were in the <hi>Oar,</hi> he might easily get them refin'd by several lying Libellers of his own Faction: But for all that, I believe they were none of his, but that
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:64305:9"/> some <hi>Janus-fac'd Conventiclers</hi> might club their wicked wits for such opprobrious conceptions, and the <hi>Cobler</hi> might with his <hi>private Printer</hi> help to bring them into the world: But however, 'tis certain he distributed them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst the <hi>disaffected</hi> in the Country, and there was no <hi>Conventicle Leader</hi> but had them, who (as their custom is to build their reputation upon others disgrace) made use of them to bring an <hi>Odium</hi> upon the Government, thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing God, like the self-justifying <hi>Pharisee,</hi> that they were not like those <hi>Publicans</hi> and sinners, the <hi>Courtiers</hi> and <hi>Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy</hi> of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Cobler</hi> presented his good friend Captain <hi>L.</hi> with these Pamphlets, who told me, much applauding them, that they were the works of the witty <hi>Cobler of Glocester;</hi> but I telling him, that the Epithete of <hi>Witty</hi> was above the capacity of a <hi>Cobler</hi> to deserve, Oh Sir, said he, you must understand he is a <hi>Glocestershire</hi>-man, and <hi>Glocester<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shire</hi> is famous for having two great <hi>Wits</hi> born in it, instan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing in Sir <hi>Thomas Overbury,</hi> and the <hi>Cobler of Glocester;</hi> but sure the Captain was much mistaken in his comparison, and might have made as proper an one of a <hi>Coach</hi> and a <hi>Wheel-barrow.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This <hi>L.</hi> was a <hi>Captain</hi> for <hi>Oliver</hi> at <hi>Ludlow,</hi> where he once signaliz'd his <hi>Valour</hi> in leading his men up, and his <hi>Wis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome</hi> in running away, saving himself to do the State more service in his <hi>Justiceship,</hi> in which Office he domineer'd o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver far better men then himself, until the <hi>turning</hi> times turn'd him out; and since for his little wit, and less learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, he hath got himself the reputation of a <hi>gifted man,</hi> the Fame whereof hath already reach'd <hi>London,</hi> and is come to the ears of a certain <hi>London Lady,</hi> famous for being a <hi>Protectress</hi> and <hi>Patroness</hi> of all Conventicles and private Pulpiteers, who having heard of his incompara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:64305:9"/> knack of <hi>Canting,</hi> takes him for a man of surpassing <hi>Pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> and Courts him by Letters for the familiarity of his acquaintanee (as he himself hath told me) And further, that her <hi>Ladiship</hi> being informed by a <hi>Shropshire</hi> Colonel, (another Fanatick brain like himself) that the <hi>dealings of the Lord</hi> had been wonderful upon him in a Sickness he once had, wrote a Letter to him, desiring to be sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfi'd how it was that the Lord dealt with him; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon he sent her a short Relation of it, but her <hi>Ladiship</hi> desiring to be more fully inform'd in all passages, he there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon (as he told me) wrote some five sheets of the <hi>dealings of the Lord upon him,</hi> and sent it to her <hi>Ladiship,</hi> who con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to my ambition, said he, intends to have it print<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</p>
            <p>I am sorry the reputation of a Person of her Quality should be fully'd by giving credit to the false informations of <hi>Canters,</hi> and <hi>Pretenders to the Spirit;</hi> wherefore to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abuse her <hi>Ladiship,</hi> I make bold to tell it abroad, that those five sheets of paper so sent to the said <hi>Lady,</hi> have nothing in them but the figments of the Authors own crazed brains, and that those <hi>Revelations, Visions, Dreams, Agonies,</hi> and other <hi>dealings of the Lord upon him,</hi> which he may write of, are nothing but his extemporary non-sense, put into a little better method, according to the description of the said Colonel, <hi>Farington,</hi> and other pretenders to <hi>Inspira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> on purpose to please her devout <hi>Ladiship.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>'Tis true, the Cap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ain took his Bed once upon a Surseit of <hi>Beef</hi> and <hi>Cabbage,</hi> and probably might then dream the <hi>Devil</hi> came to torment him before his time; whereupon in's sleep he might implore help from Heaven, and awa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, tell the people he had seen a <hi>Vision,</hi> besides he might then perhaps belch out some pieces of <hi>Canting,</hi> and his silly Visitants might take these his <hi>Eructations</hi> to be <hi>Eja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culations,</hi>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:64305:10"/> and he himself might call these the <hi>dealings of the Lord upon him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I had like to have said there is nothing can be spo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in commendation of this man, but considering that <hi>Homer</hi> commending some of his <hi>Hero</hi>'s, calls them <hi>Beef-eaters:</hi> I must needs acknowledge the Capt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>in to be praise-worthy, for I know him to be a terrible fellow at a piece of <hi>Beef.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Cobler</hi> and he were so loving in life together, that 'twas pity they were divided in death; I have heard him deplore his death, saying, there's great loss of that <hi>ingeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous man,</hi> meaning the <hi>Cobler of Glocester,</hi> whom proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly he might term ingenious, for that <hi>Stratagem</hi> he learnt of him, which was this:</p>
            <p>The <hi>Captain</hi> once complain'd to the <hi>Cobler,</hi> that his house was so haunted with <hi>Hobgoblin Justices,</hi> that he could never ke<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>p a Conventicle in's house, without great danger of being disturb'd, desiring his advice in that case; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon the <hi>Cobler</hi> counsel'd him to make a Collection to <hi>buy Cards and Dice</hi> with, which might be always ready on the Tables, so that if those <hi>uncircumcised Philistines,</hi> the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gistrates, came upon them, they might leave <hi>Preaching,</hi> and fall to <hi>Gaming;</hi> meaning, the <hi>Sisters</hi> might hide <hi>Gods books</hi> in their Plackets, and fall to the <hi>Devils,</hi> the <hi>Brothers,</hi> might let a certain Tremulation, call'd the <hi>Gentlemans Palsie,</hi> seize upon their Elbows, and every one take his turn at <hi>Hazard,</hi> and the <hi>Speaker</hi> might turn <hi>Box-keeper,</hi> and instead of <hi>Hum, ha, and ho,</hi> cry, <hi>Six to four, seven to five;</hi> so that their private <hi>House of Prayer</hi> being thus turn'd into a <hi>Temple-Hall,</hi> or <hi>Speerings</hi> Ordinary, that <hi>Den of Thieves,</hi> they might be secure enough from the <hi>Magistrates:</hi> And for this delusion it was that the <hi>Captain</hi> applauded him for an <hi>ingenious man.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whosoever is desirous to see the works of the <hi>Cobler</hi> all
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:64305:10"/> together, this <hi>Captain</hi> can satisfie his curiosity; but let him despair of getting any of them from him, for he would ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther part with the <hi>whole Duty of Man,</hi> because it seems to be written by one of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> then the least parcel of the <hi>Coblers</hi> works.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Cobler</hi> made him many Visits at his house, where he always found welcome both at Bed and Board, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver came thence empty handed, which made him like a <hi>true Beggar</hi> come the oftner, though 'twas a great distance from <hi>Glocester;</hi> but <hi>distance</hi> signifi'd nothing to the restless <hi>Cobler,</hi> for, like a <hi>Gypsie,</hi> he lov'd travelling, and never could endure to stay a fortnight in one place, in so much that he could not be said to inhabit any where: He would ramble <hi>East, West, North,</hi> and <hi>South,</hi> and find such Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factors as the <hi>Captain</hi> in every quarter; but in all his wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drings he avoided, as a Plague-infected House, the Habita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of any well-wisher to the Church of <hi>England,</hi> well knowing how unwelcome his lyes would be there: His cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stome lay all amongst malevolent <hi>Conventiclers,</hi> by whom alone he got his livelihood; and this was the reason he went so often to <hi>Kidderminster,</hi> that <hi>Nursery</hi> of Non-con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity, which was planted to be a reserve for men that may continually oppose the establish'd Government of the Church of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here it was that the <hi>Cobler</hi> found his best <hi>Masters</hi> and <hi>Mistresses,</hi> who would readily take his scandalous <hi>Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phlets,</hi> and lying <hi>Libels</hi> off his hands, striving who should gratifie him most with gifts and entertainments.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Cobler</hi> knew what kind of Stories would best please those bad Natures, wherefore he never fail'd to offend truth, that he might humor them: He had always ready some false news or other about <hi>Liberty of Conscience,</hi> some Gibe or Jear upon <hi>Episcopacy,</hi> some false scandal upon a <hi>Bishop,</hi> some nick-name for a <hi>Surplis,</hi> some Roguish Jest upon the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:64305:11"/>
               <hi>Liturgy,</hi> some lye of his own inventing upon a <hi>Parson,</hi> or some new-rais'd foul tale or other, tending to the dispa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement of the Church, Court, or State, he never was unfurnish'd of, to make those bad natur'd people merry with, who gave a <hi>Catholique Faith</hi> to all the <hi>Cobler</hi> ever said.</p>
            <p>Here it was, as well as in other places, that the impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent <hi>Cobler</hi> slandered the Right Reverend <hi>Bishop of Glocester,</hi> amongst other scandals, with falsly interpreting <hi>Grotius.</hi> You see hereby that no man can write or speak so well, but some <hi>Zoylus</hi> or <hi>Momus</hi> will rise up to find fault. <hi>Plato, Aristotle, Virgil, Livie, Seneca,</hi> and <hi>Pliny,</hi> were all carp'd at by some <hi>Criticks</hi> or other; <hi>Horace</hi> said that <hi>Homer</hi> dream'd sometimes; <hi>Demosthenes</hi> did not please <hi>Tully</hi> in all things; neither could the <hi>Bishop of Glocesters</hi> Interpretation of <hi>Grotius</hi> go free from being falsly censur'd by the more wicked then witty <hi>Cobler. Osborn</hi> was of Opinion, that <hi>ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance</hi> would be the last thing subdu'd e're the dissolution of the Universe; wherefore I believe he would have ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended the time to be very near, had he seen a <hi>Cobler</hi> write Books, and turn <hi>Critick,</hi> as this <hi>Doctor of Divillity Ralph Wallis</hi> did, making many false blows at <hi>Episcopacy,</hi> shoo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing many Fools Bolts against the Church, but never discharging one piece of Reason for whatever he said or did: The Emperor <hi>Titus</hi> (the delight of men) would com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain he had lost that day on which he had done no good Office to any one; but this <hi>Cobler</hi> the abomination of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, thought he had spent that day ill, wherein he had not done some foul turn or other to the Church or Churchmen, for 'twas meat, and drink, and cloaths to him to do such kind of mischief; and if he did not soundly ply his wicked calling, the <hi>Conventicle Leaders,</hi> and other his factious <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters</hi> and <hi>Mistresses,</hi> held him up to the Law of the <hi>Gymnoso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phists,</hi> which denies meat to them that will not work, and would allow him neither meat nor wages; wherefore he
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:64305:11"/> diligently minded his business, which was lying and slan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering, by which ungodly Trade he got his living where e're he came: But for my part, I think <hi>Whores, High-way-men, Gamesters,</hi> and <hi>Pick-pockets,</hi> get their lives by as warrant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able courses.</p>
            <p>Besides lying and slandering, he had also a <hi>thievish</hi> kind of profession which was very advantagious to him, for he did not only go snip with <hi>Conventicle Leaders,</hi> (as thieves and receivers do) for robbing the Church of its honor, and steal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing mens hearts from it, but he would put himself upon the imployment of carrying the <hi>Collections,</hi> which <hi>Quakers, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabaptists, Independents, Presbyterians,</hi> and other <hi>Conventic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers,</hi> gave to their poor or imprison'd <hi>Fellow Rebels,</hi> to strengthen them in their disobedience to the Laws of the <hi>King,</hi> and the <hi>Church;</hi> but instead of delivering what was sent, he commonly withheld either <hi>all,</hi> or the most part, for he would betray any trust to be true to himself.</p>
            <p>For all these, and a thousand other villanies, who would ever have thought this same devillish <hi>Cobler</hi> should have (preternaturally to his deserts) dy'd of a <hi>natural</hi> death: he escap'd hanging indeed, but yet he return'd to the place from whence he came; for after his many weary journeys, and indefatigable pains-taking to do mischief, his <hi>legs</hi> being fallen away with sore travel, his <hi>tongue</hi> faultring with con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinual telling lyes, and his <hi>lungs</hi> being wasted with perpetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al bawling against the Church and Church-men, like old <hi>Guy</hi> of <hi>Warwick,</hi> he return'd to his Native Country, to end his Evening where he took his Morn.</p>
            <p>At <hi>Glocester Death</hi> and the <hi>Cobler</hi> met, but he had fair warning of his coming, by a sickness which he took upon a monstrous supper of flesh one <hi>Friday night,</hi> about <hi>Lent,</hi> but for all that the <hi>Cobler</hi> had no mind to prepare himself for his death; for though the <hi>Bishop</hi> sent him a pious Exhorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to ask God forgiveness of all the injuries and dishonors
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:64305:12"/> which with his wicked <hi>tongue</hi> and <hi>pen</hi> he had done his <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>Ministers,</hi> yet instead of repenting, he quite contrarily glori'd in what he had done, and as he liv'd, so he was resolv'd to die, a <hi>Rebel</hi> to the Church and all goodness; for he was so hardned through the success of his impieties, and his long impunity, that he either could not repent, or thought he had nothing to repent of; and he either thought all the lies and slanders he had rais'd upon the Church and Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, were very <hi>venial</hi> sins, or by often telling them, and see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them pass so currantly for <hi>truths,</hi> he himself at last be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liev'd them to be so.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Death</hi> had many expostulations with him about's recove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, but considering that should he <hi>mend,</hi> yet he would never be <hi>better,</hi> and angry the world had been troubled with him so long, <hi>Death</hi> therefore took his <hi>paring knife</hi> and cut off the <hi>tatching ends</hi> of the <hi>Coblers</hi> life,</p>
            <p>This detestable <hi>Cobler</hi> (although he was <hi>intestable</hi> for his furious nature) a little e're he dy'd sent for a neighbouring <hi>Baker,</hi> who had a small faculty of writing, to make his <hi>Will,</hi> which the <hi>Cobler</hi> began to dictate, not <hi>in the Name of God, &amp;c.</hi> least in any thing he should imitate a <hi>Christian;</hi> neither did he bequeath his Soul to his Maker, not being willing perhaps to rob the <hi>devil</hi> of his due; but he began, <hi>I give to my Wife</hi> 500 l. <hi>to my Elder Daughter</hi> 200 l. <hi>to my Younger Daughter</hi> 200 l. At which the <hi>Baker</hi> asked him where all this money was, telling him, he was glad he could leave his Wife and Children so well: To which the <hi>Cobler</hi> reply'd, <hi>Neighbour, it is my Will that my Wife and Children should have so much, but if they cannot have it, I must die intestate;</hi> and so the <hi>Atheistical Rogue</hi> went out of the world, like <hi>Vespasian,</hi> with a Jest in's mouth.</p>
            <p>Though he bequeath'd 900 <hi>l.</hi> in's Will to his Wife and Daughters, yet he left them not 900 <hi>d.</hi> for he spent all his ungodly gains in's life time, and was of <hi>Heliogabalus</hi>'s lavish
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:64305:12"/> mind, that it was best for a man to be his own <hi>Heir.</hi> But if any here wonder how it came to pass that the <hi>Cobler</hi> having so many wicked ways to thrive by, dy'd in so poor a condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that a common <hi>Executioner</hi> would not have taken the pains to hang him for all he was worth, let him consider how the <hi>Devil</hi> uses to deal with <hi>Witches, Gamesters, High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way-men,</hi> and other his <hi>Slaves,</hi> seldome letting them die worth a Groat, or in their Beds, and he will be satisfi'd that <hi>Satan</hi> was very civil to his servant the <hi>Cobler,</hi> in letting him die neither of <hi>hemp nor hunger,</hi> but in a pair of <hi>hempen</hi> sheets, to put him in mind how well he had deserv'd hanging, which doubtless had fallen to his share, had that Law been in force in <hi>England</hi> which Queen <hi>Amasis</hi> once established in <hi>Egypt,</hi> whereby she punished as <hi>Felons</hi> all that could give no good account how they got their <hi>livings.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Some <hi>Fanaticks</hi> have said, that as sure as God's in <hi>Gloce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster,</hi> the <hi>Cobler of Glocester</hi>'s gone to <hi>Heaven;</hi> yet consider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that while he was alive, he <hi>mar'd</hi> more <hi>souls</hi> then ever he <hi>mended,</hi> and made more go <hi>away</hi> then ever he set <hi>upright;</hi> one may think it more probable, that if any one had been in the <hi>whispering Vault of Glocester Church,</hi> at the critical mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nute of his departure, he might have heard the <hi>Devil</hi> cry, <hi>Room for the Cobler of Glocester:</hi> whither his <hi>Soul</hi> is gone I am not bold enough to divine; but I am sure his <hi>body,</hi> which while he liv'd, nine <hi>Counties</hi> could scarcely contain, is now compris'd within nine foot of ground.</p>
            <p>Having now brought this great <hi>Minister</hi> of the <hi>Fanatick State</hi> from his clay to his dust, I shall proceed to the descrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his external parts, wherein I intend to be very cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumstantial, and then make some enquiry into his <hi>Internals,</hi> not by way of <hi>Augury,</hi> as the <hi>Romans</hi> did into the intrals of their beasts (for we must allow the <hi>Cobler</hi> to be a kind of a rational creature) but to shew you how small a share he had of Virtue, by telling how much he had of its contrary.</p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:64305:13"/>
            <p>For his person in general it was ugly, in particular any one might judge by his <hi>dog-look,</hi> that he lay lurching to play some <hi>dog-trick</hi> or other: In stature and shape he was made to run well, which agreed well with his itinerant imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; his complexion was of a Sun-burnt <hi>Gipsie</hi> colour, and his skin was rough and tawny, like <hi>sing'd Bacon;</hi> his hair was brown and brisly upon his head, but his locks were weather-turn'd, like a Barbers <hi>Show Perewig.</hi> The Scripture forbids the wearing of unseemly long hair, but the <hi>Cobler</hi> quite contrarily wore unseemly short hair, not out of his great fear to offend the Text, but out of his great feud to Decency, which by all means, like a true <hi>Non-conformist,</hi> he avoided, least he should be suspected for one of the <hi>Church of England,</hi> and so be taken for a Christian: But for all his hair was thus short and unseemly, he was as proud of it, as <hi>Commodus</hi> and <hi>Aelius Verus</hi> were of their hair powdered with the Radiments of Gold.</p>
            <p>His cloaths were always out of fashion, and every part of his Habit was as much a <hi>Non-conformist</hi> to the <hi>Mode,</hi> as he was to the <hi>Church,</hi> and he lov'd Uniformity in nothing but desormity, doing what he could by Art to make him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self more deform'd then he was by Nature: But I know not to what purpose, except as the Emperour <hi>Caracalla,</hi> having the vanity to fancy himself to be like <hi>Alexander the Great,</hi> did all he could, by holding his neck awry, and imitating other his postures to resemble him; so the <hi>Cobler</hi> might do all he could to look <hi>ugly,</hi> that he might thereby represent the <hi>Devil.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Plato</hi> was of Opinion, that Souls unwillingly departed out of fair bodies, and on the contrary; wherefore I won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that the <hi>Coblers</hi> Soul left not his body sooner, for 'twas so foul, that it might well be called the <hi>Sepulchre</hi> of his Soul.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Cobler</hi> being thus foul, it was no wonder his actions
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:64305:13"/> were no fairer, for the shape of the body commonly bears the similitude of the mind; aand therefore we may say of him, as <hi>Aristophanes</hi> said of <hi>Philocles,</hi> that his actions were soul because his person was, and the reason why he was as bad as a <hi>Witch,</hi> in doing much harm, and no good, was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause he was as foul as a <hi>Witch.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Having thus done with the <hi>Coblers</hi> Shape and Habit, I proceed to his Diet, wherein a man would judge he was very temperate, considering how little it cost him; but the truth is, he eat much, and paid little, feeding for the most part at <hi>publick</hi> entertainments; he would be as constantly at <hi>Conventicle Feasts,</hi> as a <hi>needy</hi> Gallant at my <hi>Lord Mayors:</hi> Besides, he was a great frequenter of <hi>private Christnings, Clandestine Marriages, Night-burials of Non-conformists,</hi> and other occult Solemnities, at which the <hi>Coblers</hi> presence was very necessary, especially in helping to steal a Corps in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a hole in a <hi>Church-yard,</hi> which he would do with such secresie, that the <hi>Parson</hi> and <hi>Sexton</hi> should be robb'd of their Fees, and the Corps of its <hi>Christian Burial,</hi> for which he got many a Meals Meat, and now and then some of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaseds old cloaths.</p>
            <p>He had also many other invitations by <hi>Non-conformists,</hi> which he never refused; and if at any time he was invited to two places at once to dinner, he was not so modest as a certain voracious <hi>Doctor,</hi> who in such a case is us'd to <hi>dine</hi> at the one place, and <hi>sup</hi> at the other, but the <hi>Cobler</hi> would both <hi>dine</hi> and <hi>sup</hi> at each place; nay, he was so liberal of his company at a dinner or supper, that rather then not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept of an invitation, he would commonly invite himself, bringing a <hi>stomack</hi> with him as large as his <hi>conscience;</hi> and all the while he was at's meat, by his good will he would not speak one word but what his <hi>belly</hi> prompted him to; but when that was once fill'd, he would scarce let any one have a word with him.</p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:64305:14"/>
            <p>He generally lov'd all Meats that were good, but especi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally his appetite was most s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t upon <hi>Bacon,</hi> of which food he eat so much, and so often, that as <hi>Fabius</hi> had his Name from the <hi>Latin</hi> word of <hi>Beans, Piso</hi> from that of <hi>Pease,</hi> and <hi>Lentulus</hi> from that of <hi>Lentiles,</hi> for the love they severally bore to those respective kinds of food; and as Captain <hi>L.</hi> is call'd Captain <hi>Beef,</hi> because of his great stomack to that Dish, even so the <hi>Cobler,</hi> instead of <hi>Ralph Wallis,</hi> might have been call'd <hi>Ralph Bacon,</hi> for his great appetite to it; but he would have been better <hi>Bacon,</hi> if according to his deserts he had been hang'd.</p>
            <p>In drink the Cobler vvas usually sparing vvhen it cost him any thing, but if it came in free-cost, like other <hi>Non-conformists,</hi> he vvould drink until he vvas of <hi>Copernicus</hi>'s O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion, that the World vvent round.</p>
            <p>In ancient History vve may read, hovv <hi>Anacreon</hi> vvas choak'd vvith the <hi>Husk of a Grape,</hi> and <hi>Fabius</hi> the <hi>Praetor</hi> vvith a <hi>hair in a draught of milk;</hi> and I have read in the <hi>puny Chronicles,</hi> of one choak'd vvith a <hi>Chees-cake,</hi> and another vvith the <hi>rump of a Chicken,</hi> but the last tvvo might have been alive to this day, could they have svvallovv'd as vvell as the Cobler, for vvith <hi>bawling</hi> against the <hi>Bishops,</hi> and eat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Bacon,</hi> he had made his throat so vvide and slippery, that neither meat, drink, nor lyes could ever choak him.</p>
            <p>Of Constitution he vvas strong and hardy, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lse he could not have kept his flesh so vvell upon his travel, yet he vvas not fat, but in fine travelling order; for though both vvhen he rested, and vvhen he vvas upon's journeys, he never fell from's meat, yet his continual beating upon the Hoof did keep dovvn his flesh; but for all that he vvas in good <hi>heart,</hi> until Death <hi>founder'd</hi> him.</p>
            <p>The Cobler vvas also of a bold and daring spirit, vvhich vvas a r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>sult of his poverty, for having little to loose, he ventur'd far to get something, but had he had vvealth, repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:64305:14"/> place, or any plentiful dispensation of birth or For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, he vvould have been more cool in's courage against the <hi>Laws,</hi> and not have hazarded the loss of his <hi>possessions,</hi> by so often offending against them: But he was none of <hi>Fortunes Darlings,</hi> for like <hi>Bias,</hi> he carry'd all's wealth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout him, and yet never fear'd robbing or confiscation.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Cobler</hi> thus having little to loose, had the less to fear; and therefore 'twas, that where hope of gain incou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rag'd him he was so bold in doing mischief, for he was clearly of <hi>Vespasian</hi>'s mind, that <hi>gain</hi> was sweet, though got by never so foul means; and out of this Principle it was that he never blush'd for any Villany that ever he commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, at least he was never seen to blush, for that was im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>possible, because of the <hi>brownness</hi> of his complexion, which was enough to obfuscate the <hi>Vermilion</hi> of his mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sty, had he been owner of any: But, for my part, I think he was as much a stranger to that graceful Quality, as to any kind of honesty.</p>
            <p>As the <hi>Coblers</hi> Spirits never fled to his face for shame, so neither did they ever retire to his heart for fear; for as <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liogabalus</hi> in his Oration to the Whores of <hi>Rome,</hi> admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisheth them by all means <hi>Ut frigiditatem ex cordibus &amp; pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorem ex mentibus penitus extirperent,</hi> so the <hi>Conventicle Leaders,</hi> and other the <hi>Coblers Instigators,</hi> might (not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probably) injoyn him to renounce all modesty and <hi>pusilla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimity,</hi> in executing his mischievous Function: But for all that, he stood not so stoutly to his base principles, but that he once gave back at <hi>Kidderminster;</hi> where, as he was practising his Rogueries once, Order was given to appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend him; at which, together with his guilt, he was struck into such a <hi>Panique</hi> fear, that leaving his Horse be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind him, he shew'd himself an excellent Foot-man, fly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for Religion to the House of a certain <hi>Captain,</hi> and
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:64305:15"/> Brother <hi>Saint</hi> of his, where he found none at home but the <hi>Saintess,</hi> who not only congratulated his Escape, but was ready to have protected him from further dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, by hiding him under her very Coats, if need were.</p>
            <p>How familiar they were I know not, but I am sure I have heard the Captain say, that finding this precious <hi>Saint</hi> at his house, when he came home, he not only got his horse releas'd, but at parting gave him <hi>half a Crown,</hi> thanking him for being so kind as to visit his Wife in his ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence.</p>
            <p>Some by their Hospitality to Strangers, have unawares entertained <hi>Angels;</hi> but this <hi>Captain,</hi> and his Wife, did wittingly entertain the Devillish <hi>Cobler</hi> of <hi>Gloce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Cobler</hi> was very well advis'd in taking Sanctuary at the <hi>Captains</hi> House, which (besides the advantage of its commodious Scituation by a <hi>Wood</hi>) is built for the many Trap-doors and private passages in and out, like that house which <hi>Prusias</hi> King of <hi>Bithinia</hi> gave <hi>Hannibal</hi> the <hi>Carthaginian,</hi> after <hi>Scipio</hi> conquer'd him, to secure himself in, from the surprizals of the <hi>Romans,</hi> his own Country not daring to conceal him.</p>
            <p>In a word, this House of the <hi>Captains</hi> is every way so cunningly contrived, as though he designed it, either for a Receptacle to such <hi>Rogues</hi> as the <hi>Cobler</hi> was, or for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self to sculk in, or make his Escape out of, in case his endeavours fail him in some bad designs he is thought to have in hand: And another argument he secures himself from such a Chance is, his holding his Lands, Livings, and all that ever he by hook or crook is worth, in other mens Names.</p>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:64305:15"/>
            <p>For this <hi>Captains</hi> Religion, if we take his own word for't he's a <hi>Latitudinarian</hi> taking up that denomination perhaps from the <hi>immensity</hi> of his Conscience, and so he may as well call himself a <hi>Longitudinarian,</hi> but however he may gloss upon himself in plain English he's a <hi>Leveller,</hi> that wo'ud with all his heart have the present power planed that he might insult over is again.</p>
            <p>He is much of the nature of the <hi>Cobler of Gloucester</hi> in op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probious Language against the Government of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and railing against the decent Ceremonies there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, in so much that the loss of the <hi>Atlantick Cobler</hi> in those parts will be the lesse, so long as this <hi>Herculian Captain</hi> is a live to support the Fanatick faction.</p>
            <p>He has all the false news of <hi>Liberty of Conscience,</hi> being granted, much of which is, of his own raising, and he is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually talking of the <hi>necessity</hi> of such a toleration, being prompted to it by the <hi>Advantage</hi> he proposes to himself thereby: nay he is so vehement for it, that like other self aiming <hi>Non conformists</hi> he lays all the misfortunes of the Nation and miscarriages of State to the want of it. So have I heard him hypocritically bewail the misery, he said the Countrey was like to fall into in that the Cattle went not off this Summer, and this he gave for a reason.</p>
            <p>The <hi>King</hi> (quoth he) having put out a Proclamation against Conventicles, the <hi>Non conformists</hi> who (said he) have got all the <hi>Money</hi> of the Kingdom into their hands, have thereupon called in all their money, being resolved to put cut no more untill such time as <hi>Liberty of Conscience</hi> shall be granted, whereupon the <hi>Grasiers,</hi> about <hi>London</hi> failing of their usuall supplyes of money upon Interest from the money'd <hi>Non-conformist,</hi> cannot take the Cattle off the <hi>Drovers</hi> hands, who by consequence can buy no more from the Countrey <hi>Farmers</hi> who by consequence cannot pay their Rent, and by consequence must be begger'd. By this kind of argumenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:64305:16"/> he went about to prove the Lands misery, but what half witted man would not deny his argument, well know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that the onely reason why Cattle went not off in the Countrey this Summer was for want of grass about <hi>London.</hi> He indeavoured also to prove the reason of the decay of <hi>Trading</hi> and <hi>Merchandizing</hi> in the Nation to be onely the want of <hi>Liberty of Conscience</hi> by such like frivolous arguments which can make no impression upon either wise or honest people, but by this means the <hi>Malleable</hi> vulgar are stirred up to oppose the Laws by Calumniating words and illegall assemblies, which otherwise would live quietly under the Government, imputing their mis-fortunes to more proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble causes. And this is the constant practice of <hi>Conventi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle-leaders</hi> to bring an odium upon the Government, and make their <hi>Mundungos</hi> doctrine take the better amongst their deluded followers whose brains being over heated by the <hi>sulphurious</hi> reports of their <hi>Hot-headed Leaders,</hi> they can judge no better what is meant by all that <hi>zealous</hi> preaching they hear then a <hi>feaverish</hi> pallat can relish the true gusto of the Meat it tasts, but as some take <hi>bad</hi> Tobacco commending it for the best, so the ears of <hi>Conventiclers</hi> do greedily drink in the doctrine of their <hi>factious</hi> leaders, and their faith swallows it for the best, not discerning the <hi>Gunpowder</hi> that's in it to blow up Church and State.</p>
            <p>Much might be said of this <hi>Captain</hi> to shew you what an <hi>admirer</hi> he was of the <hi>Cobler</hi> but I on purpose omit him to make some conjectures of the <hi>Coblers</hi> Religion, which truly was so <hi>Mongril like</hi> that I know not what to call him. He joyn'd himself to <hi>Independants, Anabaptists, Quakers and Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterians,</hi> and agreed with them all in railing against the times and crying down the authority of them in rule. He something resembled a <hi>Jew,</hi> also in his malice to Christian Church Men, but his <hi>Bacon</hi> devouring principle may satisfie all the World he was no <hi>Jew.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:64305:16"/>
            <p>Some thought he might be a <hi>Jesuite</hi> sculking under the shape of a <hi>Cobler,</hi> because he would so cunningly insinuate lyes unto mens unwary hearts, but truly he never shewed himself <hi>Popishly</hi> affected in any thing except in bearing a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petual grudge to the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and he was so far from being of that Church, which like a <hi>painted Whore</hi> is all for ceremonies that quite contrarily he favour'd those Churches most which like <hi>dirty</hi> sluts were for no ceremonies at all, besides his <hi>illeterature</hi> might secure him from the scandal of being a <hi>Jesuite,</hi> for though he had polluted many books with his <hi>pitchy</hi> thumbs, and continually poring upon them, yet he could not arrive to any perfection in his <hi>Mother</hi> tongue, for all his writing too, he was still a <hi>Cobler,</hi> and though he confidently courted <hi>Minerva</hi> yet she constantly slighted him, disdaining to frame a <hi>Mercury</hi> out of a degene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate <hi>wooden Cobler,</hi> or to set her Jewels so plain as in the <hi>dull Spirit</hi> of a base <hi>Mecanick,</hi> she scorn'd to dignifie him with a <hi>Cothurne or Buskin,</hi> whose conversation had been more with old <hi>Boots</hi> then <hi>Books.</hi> This mov'd his Irascible faculty a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst her Minions, and because she would not vouchsafe him her favours, he therefore villify'd them in others, to speak more plain the <hi>Cobler</hi> contemn'd learning in others, because he found it wanting in himself, saying it was invented by conjurors and <hi>Papists,</hi> and that <hi>Languages</hi> were nothing but the <hi>confusion of Babel,</hi> but all his feud against learning and learned men arose from nothing but the defect of that grace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful qualification in himself. So it is an ordinary thing for deformed persons to despise beauty (that <hi>very glorious gift of the Gods</hi> as <hi>Homer</hi> calls it) in others, calling it pride, and effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minateness, when as they themselves wou'd be much more proud had they any thing to be proud of, and so there are many <hi>upstart conventicle Leaders,</hi> generated out of <hi>Mecanicks</hi> or <hi>Tradesmen,</hi> who having that base quality of the <hi>Devil,</hi> to wish all in as bad a condition as themselves, would willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:64305:17"/> have all as ignorant of learning as they are, and hence i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> is that they cry out so loud against the <hi>Rhetorical Divines</hi> of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> crying up plainness of speech altogether and all out of a conscious knowledge of their own defects.</p>
            <p>It's strange to me that these Men should parallell them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves with <hi>Paul</hi> as they usually do, when as they are no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing like him, for whereas <hi>Paul</hi> was said to be mad for his much learning, these men may be said to be mad for their little learning, yet they make the Spirit (like occult quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties) a shelter from the suspicion of their ignorance. They hate the succinct brevity of the Laconick dialect, because 'tis out of their reach, and admire <hi>Cicero</hi> for his long wind, but not for his eloquence, because they cannot imitate it. They despise the <hi>orders</hi> of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and undervalue men in <hi>degrees,</hi> because they were never capable of orders not degrees. They speak against <hi>Universityes,</hi> because they were no members of them, saying <hi>Popery,</hi> is taught there ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king that advantage perhaps from several books of <hi>Philosophy &amp;c.</hi> Which were written by <hi>Roman Catholicks,</hi> and so the <hi>Cobler</hi> took occasion to say once of <hi>All Souls Colledge</hi> in <hi>Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford,</hi> that it was a Colledge of <hi>Papists,</hi> either because there are so many <hi>civil Lawyers</hi> there, whom he took to be limbs of the <hi>Pope,</hi> or because of the painted Chappel, where he might see Saint <hi>Laurence</hi> pictured with his <hi>Grid-Iron</hi> whom perhaps he might take to be some <hi>Popes Red Herring</hi> Broiler, and this alone is enough to convince all the World he was no <hi>Jesuite.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Some thought he might be a <hi>Quaker</hi> for his contempt of Magistrates but he differ'd from that sect in that it was not against his principles to <hi>swear,</hi> for when he broach'd any lye upon the Church or Church men, to make it gain the more credit he wou'd ordinarily aver the truth of it upon his <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scienc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> a thing he could never remember himself owner of,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:64305:17"/> yet he wou'd swear by it, just as if <hi>Quartilla</hi> should have sworn by her <hi>Virginity,</hi> whereas she had been so long an <hi>Whore,</hi> that she could never remember her self a Maid.</p>
            <p>For my part I incline to believe he was a <hi>Presbyterian</hi> for these two reasons, first because he wou'd lie and slander like that old caluminator the <hi>Devil,</hi> and secondly because of his obstinate humour to resist any command, though never so legally injoyn'd and this he shew'd to the very last in his ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nest request that he might by no means be buried in <hi>Flannin,</hi> for no other reason then to manifest his contempt of the Law.</p>
            <p>I am now quite tired with this <hi>everlasting</hi> subject the <hi>Cob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler,</hi> but ere I end with him I cannot omit to tell you what was in his great and high disdaining mind to have effected ere he dy'd; and truly as <hi>Ovid</hi> complains to <hi>Augustus</hi> that it griev'd him more then his Exile to be banished e're he had finished a work he had begun even so it vext the <hi>Cobler</hi> more then his death to be cut off ere he had accomplished the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sign he had in hand, which was this. The <hi>Cobler</hi> having it predicted it to him either by his own false spirit, or by some of the self designing Jesuitically principled <hi>conventicle Lead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers,</hi> that the present <hi>Parliament</hi> upon this their present meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing would be dissolued, had designed to gallop, go, ride, and run over all parts to stir up the people to give their votes for such new <hi>Parliament men</hi> as would be sure to pass the Bill for such a toleration; to this intent he was resolv'd to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dergo all pains and perils, by posting up and down to carry the <hi>conventicle Leaders</hi> impious exhortations, to scatter their <hi>pamphlets</hi> or use any other wicked means he should be put upon by those his instigators, who having that one <hi>absurdity of Liberty of conscience,</hi> once granted them, know very well that a <hi>toleration</hi> of all their guilded impieties will of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessity follow.</p>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:64305:18"/>
            <p>Doubtless the <hi>Cobler</hi> had been a stout stickler for them in this project, had not envious death robb'd them, and the <hi>Gallows of him,</hi> but for all he's gone, there are many <hi>conven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle Leaders,</hi> who have proceeded in this design with such success, that they make no question but a little time will effect what they so much affect.</p>
            <p>That they may get this misterious, but profitable thing call'd <hi>Liberty of conscience</hi> conceded, they have, and do still practice the Method of the <hi>Devil</hi> tempting the Frailty of the Wife, who being deluded her self commonly draws her Husband in to be a Fool with her for company.</p>
            <p>They know very well 'tis no hard matter to deceive <hi>silly women</hi> whose sex hath ever been Famous for credulity and devotion and therefore it is that as the <hi>Devil</hi> began with <hi>Eve</hi> to beguil <hi>Adam,</hi> so they first set upon the Wives with their desembled piety that they may more easily gain the Husbands to their side, who either out of <hi>Love</hi> cannot, or <hi>fear</hi> dare not deny the demands of their Wives though never so imperti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent, but give their votes for a <hi>toleration</hi> abroad because forc'd to it at home.</p>
            <p>They easily lead away captive silly women, who being no less fond of strange <hi>Doctrine</hi> then they are of strange flesh, do more readily admit them into their hearts, houses, purses, and beds, but men being of sollider Judgements and deeper understandings do not so readily submit, their reasons to be tyranniz'd over by <hi>conventicle Leaders</hi> but discern their frau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulancy through some cra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y or other of their self ended dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>simulation, hence it is that look into any conventicle you find so few Men and so many Women.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mother Shipton</hi> prophecy'd that seven women should follow <hi>one</hi> man, but behold here's a greater wonder come to pass in our time for now a days its an ordinary thing to see not 7 but <hi>sevenscore</hi> women follow one single simpleton that can but pretend to the Spirit and talk Familiarly with his Maker.</p>
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:64305:18"/>
            <p>These Women that make conventicles swell thus, are for the most part either discontented wives, melancholly wid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows or stale Maids who for their foul shapes, ill looks and worse conditions despair of ever having Husbands; having been cross'd in their loves or thwarted in their ambition they presently turn abandoners of the World, and as in <hi>Italy,</hi> such run into <hi>Cloysters,</hi> so in <hi>England</hi> into <hi>conventicles,</hi> they first run out of their <hi>wits</hi> for love, jealousie or anger, and then run out of the Church to the next <hi>conventicle Leaders,</hi> who by their strict profession o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>zeal for liberty of Conscience,</hi> and cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ningly applying <hi>texts of Scripture,</hi> to their Fancies possess them in such sort that the powerful word of God assisted with the Rhetorick of <hi>Divines</hi> is not of efficacy sufficient to reclaim them to the Church, but they cry they have soft hearts and tender consciences when alas all their <hi>tenderness and softness</hi> lys in their heads, and they may be better cur'd by <hi>Doctor Graves, More-fields Physick</hi> then any <hi>Doctors Divinity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The men that resort to these <hi>conventicles</hi> for the most part either want wit, honesty or Government over thir wives, I need not say much of their dispotions, for by the sign that nature hath hung our conjecture may be made what qualities they have within, there are <hi>few good countenances,</hi> amongst them and therefore <hi>few good conditions</hi> are to be expected from them you may ordinarily see discontent or Folly in their looks, and for my part I can say that I scarce ever beheld an <hi>ingeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous</hi> Face amongst them, neither can the <hi>conventicle Leaders,</hi> boast of many handsome <hi>she Proselites</hi> amongst them, for their's not one of them can say as <hi>Juno</hi> did to <hi>Aeolus, sunt mihi bis Septem puaestanti corpore Nymphae.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But theirs many of them can say <hi>sunt mihi bis centum defor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mi corpore Vernae.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I remember I have read of a good <hi>Pope</hi> in former time, who seeing some <hi>Brittish</hi> Captives expos'd to sale at <hi>Rome,</hi> was mov'd with pitty that so handsome shap'd and well com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plection'd
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:64305:19"/> people had not the light of the <hi>Gospel</hi> amongst them, and thereupon sent some over into <hi>Brittanny</hi> to instruct them in <hi>Christianity,</hi> but I believe that had they been no better aspected nor handsomlyer compos'd then those which <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venticles</hi> for the most part consist of, he would not have been so inamour'd of their <hi>persons</hi> as to wish their <hi>Souls</hi> so well.</p>
            <p>As the <hi>bodies</hi> of all <hi>conventicles</hi> are generally deform'd so the <hi>Major</hi> part of the heads of them are but <hi>Minors</hi> in comly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness for my part <hi>I</hi> know few <hi>conventicle Leaders</hi> so handsome that if <hi>I</hi> met them in a morning <hi>I</hi> might presage to my self good luck that day, as the <hi>Romans</hi> us'd to do when they met comly persons, but rather <hi>I</hi> should judge the meeting of one of these <hi>scarcrow Divines</hi> fatidical as <hi>Septimus severus</hi> did the meeting of a <hi>Blackamoor,</hi> but their aspect is not so terrible to me as to hear them so frequently bawling in <hi>Conventicles,</hi> for considering that these kind of Ravens croack'd mighty loud before that shower of blood fell in our Land, it may be an omen that the like deluge is now threatned.</p>
            <p>If we strictly inquire into the originals of these <hi>conventicle leaders,</hi> which make all this ado in the Nation, we shall find that more of them came our of the <hi>four and twenty companys</hi> then <hi>Universitys,</hi> and that more belong to <hi>Halls</hi> then <hi>Colledges</hi> who becoming <hi>free men</hi> in Divinity, ere they had serv'd an <hi>apprenticeship</hi> in the <hi>University,</hi> because they cannot now keep open shop, are turn'd <hi>Journeymen</hi> prayers and preachers to as many as are so mad as to hire them. Thesemen have for the most part but little wit, but they have the fortune to perswade others to have as little sense as themselves they wriggle them selves into favour with a company of <hi>Pettycoat</hi> converts, and think they have power to lead about a Sister or a Wife, as well as <hi>Paul,</hi> ask any of them how they dare be so bold as to preach and they are ready to say with <hi>Paul, Woe is unto me if</hi> I <hi>preach not the Gospel,</hi> but woe is unto the Gospel,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:64305:19"/> for being Preach'd by such as these, and may not they as well prove the Lawfulness of their Cheating the World from <hi>Jacobs cheating his brother Esau?</hi> They are fuller of Texts then Proofs, yet they will make pretty fond interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations of Scripture to tickle the minds of their Proselites, and very cunningly wrest a Scripture to defend their unwar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantable practices by, but the <hi>Devil</hi> had his <hi>Scriptum est</hi>'s as well as they.</p>
            <p>They have the voice of <hi>Tragaedians,</hi> and the gesture of <hi>Comedians,</hi> and act the <hi>Hypocrite</hi> to the life. They ramp and tear in the Pulpit as though they wou'd pull their Maker out of Heaven, and keep such a bawling in their Prayers, as though they either bid defiance to the Magistrates, or thought God was not amongst them; but when they pray for the King, they fall their voice as though they were afraid their Prayers should reach Heaven, and I believe that their praying for the King is but as an honest Parson once pray'd for <hi>Oliver,</hi> who in's prayer said; <hi>And since O Lord we are commanded to pray for our Enemies, we beseech thee to be mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciful to the Lord Protector,</hi> leaving him thus like a Plague in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected House, with a <hi>Lord have mercy upon him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Others there are of the <hi>Conventicle-Leaders,</hi> that have Learning indeed, but withall some humour or other, that (as the <hi>wild Gourds</hi> spoil'd the porridge) marreth all: They are peremptory in asserting their own Opin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ons, not caring what Troubles or Combustions they raise in the Church, so that they can but maintain their own fancies.</p>
            <p>Others are of strange complaining humours, obstinate, pettish, froward, and as various as the <hi>Neutrum modo, mas modo vulgus,</hi> no Government or Governours can please them long, but they will continually find fault.</p>
            <p>Some men are for all times, but these men I am now speaking of are against all times. They wish'd for the <hi>Rightfull Monarch</hi> e're they had him, and now they have
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:64305:20"/> him they wou'd live <hi>Anarchically</hi> under him: The truth is, they are men compos'd of nothing but <hi>Discord,</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore 'tis no marvel if the <hi>vocal and instrumental Harmony</hi> of the Church cannot recreate them; they are of <hi>black melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choly</hi> Constitutions, and therefore no wonder if a <hi>white Surplis</hi> offend them. They know that their Sermons wou'd be no more the worse, if preach'd in a Surplis, than the last <hi>Lord Mayors</hi> Dinner wou'd have been if he had entred the <hi>Temple</hi> with his Sword <hi>down,</hi> yet they stand upon their <hi>punctilios,</hi> and rather then be constrain'd to come to the Lord's Table in <hi>clean Linnen,</hi> they'l in a slovingly way make a private meal in a Chamber, and there's many of their followers that will refuse the bread of Life, if not served up after their own nasty way.</p>
            <p>Others there are of these <hi>Conventicle-Leaders,</hi> and that a very considerable number, who incourag'd through the hope of gain and preferment, ingag'd themselves so far in fomen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the late Rebellion, that they think they cannot in honour now come back; besides, what wou'd their followers say, who have known them <hi>Rebells</hi> formerly, should they now turn honest men? Yet there's some of them could withall their hearts shake hands, and be friends with the Church of <hi>England,</hi> could the World as clearly forget, as the King hath mercifully forgiven, what they have done against it. This is the party there is most danger of; for the others only feed upon the Ulcers of the times, and like <hi>Physicians,</hi> are best in Distemper'd times: But these stand stiffly to their Old base principles, and do all they can to bring all into Confusion again. They are immoderate in their Demands, and high in their Carriage, as though they meant to make the <hi>Church</hi> compound for its <hi>Peace,</hi> and the <hi>King</hi> for his <hi>Quiet,</hi> upon their own terms: Ask them to condescend to any proposal, and they are resolv'd before hand to deny it, like <hi>Alexander</hi> the Great, who swore to the Ambassadours of the <hi>Lamp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saceni</hi>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:64305:20"/> before-hand, that he wou'd do every thing contrary to what they requested. And this nature they sufficiently ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifested in their peremptory Carriage, in the Treaty at the <hi>Savoy,</hi> where the <hi>Bishops</hi> met them with Arms open, ready to imbrace them, but they behav'd themselves so there, as though their main business were either to obtain a denial in their Demands, or to tell the <hi>Bishops</hi> plainly that it was as much in vain for them to expect that they would ever be friends to the <hi>Church of England,</hi> as for the <hi>Romans</hi> to have hop'd for peace from <hi>Hannibal,</hi> when as he had sworn to be their perpetual Enemy; nay, further should the <hi>Bishops</hi> have descended to ask them, wherein they might do them any ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable office, assuring them their requests should end in no denial. I believe, there were some of that Legation, from the Disaffected party, could with all their hearts have an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swered as <hi>Demochares,</hi> one of the <hi>Athenian Ambassadours,</hi> did <hi>King Philip of Macedon,</hi> in such a case, telling him that the only way for him to please the <hi>Athenians,</hi> was to take a Rope and hang himself.</p>
            <p>They so exercise their Enmities against the Church of <hi>England,</hi> that they leave no room for Reconciliation; and that <hi>Exclamation</hi> in <hi>Homer,</hi> seems to be the <hi>Motto</hi> of their inclinations to the Church.</p>
            <q>Aut tu me tollas, aut ego te.</q>
            <p>They are a sort of <hi>Animals, ferae naturae,</hi> they are gone from the Church, <hi>sine animo revertendi,</hi> like <hi>Noah's Dove,</hi> they went out from it, but like <hi>Noah's Raven,</hi> they will never return again: They have the ambition of <hi>Caesar,</hi> for they wou'd rather be the <hi>Heads</hi> of Conventicles, than the <hi>second men</hi> in the Church of <hi>England.</hi> They say now they are for the <hi>King,</hi> but 'tis but just like the unfortunate <hi>Essex's,</hi> crying out for the <hi>Queen;</hi> 'tis true, they wou'd have
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:64305:21"/> the King reign, but 'tis with this <hi>proviso,</hi> that they may <hi>rule.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Christians</hi> of old, wanted not power but will to free themselves from the Tyrannous persecutions of the <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens and Infidells,</hi> but these kind of Christians want not will but power to throw off the legal Instunctions of the Magistrates of Church and State, who are their fellow-Christians, and never offended them, but in their desire to amend them.</p>
            <p>They are too ambitious to be Devout, and all their strict profession of Zeal, Justice and Piety, is for nothing, but to disguise their secret and ambitious self-ends; all their crying down the <hi>Bishops</hi> is out of no other design than that <hi>they</hi> may come up, and to this end alone it is that by their scandalous imputations and false suggestions sometimes in Conventicles, and alwayes in private conferences, they daily detract from their honour, and represent them to their abused followers unworthy the places they hold. They slander their Actions, deride their Vesture, and do what they can to lessen their Authority, that they may thereby (like true <hi>Sophisters of Hell</hi>) undermine the power of the <hi>Prince.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>They Nick-name the vertues of the <hi>Bishops</hi> with vitious imputations, calling their provident saving for the repair of their Palaces, Families and Relations (which were ruin'd, decay'd, and begger'd by such hollow-hearted <hi>Machiavilli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> as themselves) sordid Covetousness, and the liberality of others, extravagant profuseness; and such a construction as this have some of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>m made of the <hi>Arch-Bishops.</hi> Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificence in erecting to so good an intent that <hi>stately Pile at Oxford,</hi> saying of it like <hi>Judas,</hi> to what end's all this wast? might not the <hi>Arch-Bishop</hi> have expressed his liberality more piously in rebuilding so many Churches, as the money thrown away upon that <hi>Play-house</hi> (as they call it) would have done; not that they care for Churches, so long as they
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:64305:21"/> are under Episcopal Government, any more than <hi>Judas</hi> did for the poor, but that they may have them ready built to their hands against they come to be <hi>Masters,</hi> which they hope shortly to be, and to this end alone it is that, <hi>Malunt allatrare Episcop<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rum famam, quam imitari eorum virtutes, sed quam parum haec conveniunt cum officio hominis Christiani cui nihil legavit servator n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ster praeter pacem suam et charitatis com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendationem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Monks and Fryers</hi> in the dawning of the Reformation, that they might beat down the reputation of the reformed Churches, and keep their own scabb'd flock together, told in their Sermons that the <hi>Hereticks</hi> (as they call'd them of the Reformed Churches) did in their meetings eat Children, and such like <hi>Bug-bear-tales,</hi> whereby they inrag'd their a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bused followers more violently against them: and such like <hi>Jesuitical</hi> practices do the <hi>private Gospellers</hi> now adayes use to derogate from the Obedience due to the <hi>Venerable F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s</hi> of the Church, they have alwayes ready some false definiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>Episcopacy</hi> that it is nothing but a new word for <hi>Popery,</hi> or of the Common-prayer, that it is nothing but the <hi>Mass in English,</hi> or as <hi>Blaky the conventicle leader</hi> said of it in his Scotch tone, that it was good for nothing but to light a pipe of Tobacco with. And many other unchristian means they have to bring an Odium upon the Government and Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours of the Church, by which their misled <hi>Proselites</hi> are so inflam'd against them, that the men could find in their hearts like <hi>Sampson</hi> to burn all the standing Corn rather than the <hi>Philistine</hi> Church-men should have a tenth part of it, and the Women, if Hemp were hard to come by, wou'd readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, like the <hi>Carthaginian Matrons,</hi> cut their hair to make Ropes to hang them, but wou'd pawn their Rings, Bodkins, and Thimbles, to supply their own factious Prachers. And I believe there's some of these self-seeking <hi>Conventicle-leaders</hi> cou'd wish as <hi>Caligula did of Rome,</hi> that all the Bishops had
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:64305:22"/> but one Neck, but yet have hypocrisie enough to cloak their wicked minds with a pretence of zeal for Reformation, which they seem so piping hot with, as though like <hi>Porcia,</hi> they had swallow'd burning Coals, or cou'd spit fire like a Juggler in the faces of them that oppose it, but for all their <hi>Sulphurous Zeal,</hi> which like <hi>Aetna,</hi> they breath out now for Religion, it is my opinion they would not burn with the like ardour, shou'd they come to power (which God forbid.) These are the men so cry'd up for true piety and Devotion now a dayes; <hi>Ita enim judicat hoc incipiens et infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cetum seculum, eos solos vero zelo censeri oportere, qui intem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peranter debacchantur in eos qui iisdem sacris sunt initiati, et in plerisque servant eadem doctrinam extra paucissimos articulos, quibus ad liquidum pervistigandis impar est mens imbecillis Mortalium, in quibus sobria simplicitas et ingenua fragilitatis suae notitia confessioque vincit manem sui fiduciam et periculosam sciendi curiositatem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If we strictly inquire into all these <hi>Conventicle-leaders</hi> course of living, for all their oral sanctity and heavenly looks, we shall find that they are but <hi>Men</hi> subject to eating and drinking as well as the <hi>Cobler.</hi> They have not the guift of not erring themselves, for all their freeness to censure others. For all their Meager vissages and thin jaws (which are but results of their pale envy and black melancholy) like <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raoh's lean kine,</hi> they devour the fat things of the Land. They have not altogether the continence of <hi>Sophocles,</hi> nor the sobriety of the <hi>Sabines,</hi> but in some measure the Luxury of <hi>Lucullus,</hi> neither are they so moderate in their pleasures of the flesh, as some think they are. Though they some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times after a full meal fast all day, yet for the most part they feast the night following, eating and drinking like <hi>French Ordinary men.</hi> Their praying and preaching in a house seems to me but like one of their tedious Graces be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore their Feasts, for come into any day conventicle or night
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:64305:22"/> assembly and you may hear the <hi>Jack wherring,</hi> which is the measure of their discourse instead of an hour-glass, and so their exercises are longer or shorter according to the quality of the meat that's roasting. If a Chine or a Surloyn of Bief be at the fire, it will force the speaker to repetition ere it be ready, and make him sweat and drop like it, ere it be enough roasted, but then he gets some Cordial draught or other to keep his melted grease from his heart.</p>
            <p>These men have not drank of the <hi>Clitorian Fountain,</hi> that they should be so much out of Charity with Wine, as they would have the World believe, but, so it come not from the <hi>Kings head</hi> or the <hi>Miter,</hi> they'l drink it though it come from the <hi>Devil Tavern:</hi> and some of them with Old <hi>Cato,</hi> will now and then take a cup too much.</p>
            <p>Did they so much abhor Wine, as they pretend, their followers wou'd not be so ready to present them with whole baskets of it as they are. For my part I believe there's some of them love good Wine so well, that if I heard them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wail the loss of <hi>Candia,</hi> I should not judge it altogether, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause a branch of <hi>Christendom</hi> is lopt oss, but in a great mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure, because the <hi>Wine destroying Turk,</hi> hath destroyed all <hi>Muskadine</hi> Vines, which were us'd to yield them such fine preparative and restorative draughts, yet they may undergo that loss with the more patience as long as their Enemy the <hi>Turk</hi> is withheld from the <hi>Canary Ilands,</hi> for sack taken in a larger quantity is as good for a <hi>long-winded Saint</hi> as <hi>Mus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kadine.</hi> I will not stand to particularize upon these <hi>Conven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle-leaders,</hi> as the Cobler did upon the Clergy of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> but I say of them in general that their Souls, dwell in their senses, and the beastly commendation of <hi>eating and drinking well</hi> is proper to them all. They have nothing in them that distinguishes them from other men, but an affected impudence and studdy'd hypocrisy, with which they blear the eyes of the World, and dissemble themselves
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:64305:23"/> into people's houses, eating and drinking so long upon their cost, that they have brought the Tap of some of their E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>states upon stoop. They are true devourers of Widows houses, and all of them make a gain of their pretended Godliness: though they seem by their zealous Preaching to aim at nothing more than the good of their Proselite's Souls, yet they intermix that Doctrine amongst it. That <hi>those that preach the Word, should live by the Word,</hi> by vertue of which Text that canting <hi>Grocer in Tuttl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>-street</hi> layes claim to a share of that money which was left to be distributed by five pounds a piece to such a number of <hi>Conventicle-leaders,</hi> who with their Magical <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eal had infatuated a certain Ze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lot to make his Testament <hi>ad tales impias causas.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Gain is the Mistress they all Court, and all their Devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion tends to that center. Thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> alone makes them so boldly to hazard being imprison'd, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>or by throwing themselves into prison they gain as much as the <hi>Broken-Aldermen.</hi> For their followers feed them <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> with contributions and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sents when they are in Custody, that the Magistrates can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not do them a greater injury than to rel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ase them.</p>
            <p>I have heard among this party, that one of them got a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove two hundred pounds by his weekes Imprisonment, but yet desir'd his Liberty, beca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>se probably it is more ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantagious to him, and he attain'd it by vertue of <hi>Preva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rication,</hi> which set an Offender taken in the manner at Liberty, for want of a little formality in his commitment, but what said <hi>Oliver St. John</hi> to the <hi>Earl of Strafford,</hi> plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding for the benefit of the Law. <hi>F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>stra legi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> auxi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ium implorat qui contra legem p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ccat,</hi> and further sai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> he, <hi>Foxes and Wolves are to be knock'd on the head as they are found.</hi>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ut are not these men liker to Foxes, who with the fire-brands of their Zeal put all into combustions.</p>
            <p>And <hi>Westminster-Hall</hi> had n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed beware that they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>un not <hi>Littleton</hi> up into as narrow a Room, as <hi>it</hi> has run <hi>Justinian:</hi>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:64305:23"/> for these men aim to have all Laws be given from the Pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit.</p>
            <p>It is best that all beware of these <hi>Sodalitates</hi> in time, for there have been too many fatal accidents by them to teach all men the danger of security, and it is manifest that they have prov'd as destructive to Common-wealths as the <hi>Bacchanals of Rome and Athens.</hi> And if the followers of these <hi>Conventicle-leaders</hi> wou'd but open their eyes they might discern that the good preaching they hear is us'd to ends, that many of them will be asham'd to own.</p>
            <p>But they are still blinded either by their own self-wills, or by the mist of piety, which their leaders cast before their eyes, by which means they can no better judge between good and evil intentions, than Children looking through a green or red prospective, can discern the true colour of the object they behold.</p>
            <p>These men counterfeit Divines so well, that 'tis hard to know them from such, but an <hi>Ape's an Ape,</hi> though it be like a man, and who with <hi>Agesilaus</hi> would not refuse to hear one counterfeit a Nightingal when they can hear the Nightingal her self.</p>
            <p>Thus much I have made bold to say of <hi>Conventicle-leaders,</hi> because some of them were the <hi>Instigators,</hi> and all the <hi>Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provers</hi> of what the wicked Cobler said or did to the scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dal of the Church and Church-men, and were not I afraid of bringing a swarm of Wasps about my ears. I could give a more particular account what they are, what they design, why they swarm so, like <hi>Padua Doctors,</hi> about <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:64305:24"/> in so much that there's above <hi>twenty</hi> of them in one Parish, pestring the City worse than ever <hi>Venice</hi> was with <hi>Jesuites.</hi> Much I could say, and not wrong truth, as they by the mouth of the <hi>Cobler</hi> did, for they us'd him but like as the Devil did his Images in former times, but I am afraid I have said more than I shall be thank'd for by the factious Conventiclers and Conventicle-leaders: yet if any of that progeny of Momus, blame me for sharpness of humour against them, I tell them that <hi>praefervida et ignea eorum in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genia, quae nihil evomunt in ecclesiam praeter atroces minas et inexpiabiles iras, hanc justam mihi moverunt bilem.</hi> And that my <hi>tender Conscience</hi> would not permit me to Court their baseness with respect, and I hope they will not deny me <hi>liberty of Conscience.</hi> I have said nothing of them but what I either know or believe in my Conscience, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I desire, that they, who are so strongly bent for tole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, would grant me my free opinion amongst them.</p>
            <p>If they blame me for taking their dead <hi>Lyon the Cobler</hi> by the beard, and speaking so ill of him now he's gone. I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer, it was because I never either heard or knew any bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of him while he was alive: neither would I have foul'd any paper with him, or troubled my self to ransack his life thus to the infamy of <hi>Non-conformists</hi> (against whom I have not an irreconcileable enmity) but that I could not indure a <hi>President</hi> of so high a nature should pass unregi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster'd, or not taken notice of. <hi>Procopius</hi> in his Book <hi>de bello Persico</hi> tells us how <hi>Theophilus</hi> finding the Image of an Ape which the <hi>Persians</hi> worshipped for a God, set it up in a publick place, least it should be denyed in Ages to come, that the <hi>Gentiles</hi> once had such a God; and so I lighting upon <hi>Ralph Wallis,</hi> whom the <hi>Conventiclers</hi> and
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:64305:24"/>
               <hi>Conventicle-leaders</hi> ador'd for a <hi>Saint,</hi> have thus set him out to posterity, least hereafter it should be deny'd that those <hi>Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conformists</hi> had once such a <hi>Saint</hi> as the <hi>Cobler</hi> of <hi>Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cester.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>